Think of the wisest person you know.
想想你认识的最聪明的人。
What is it that makes them wise?
是什么让他们智慧？
What qualities do they have?
他们有什么特质？
Does wisdom mean the same for you as it does for me?
智慧对你来说和对我来说意义相同吗？
All cultures value wisdom, but not all cultures agree on its definition.
所有文化都重视智慧，但并非所有文化都认同其定义。
For some, the focus is on intelligence, while others emphasise compassionate love for others.
对一些人来说，重点是智力，而另一些人则强调对他人的博爱。
In some cultures, a spiritual component is required to be considered wise.
在某些文化中，具有精神层面的特质才能被认为有智慧。
Are there any aspects of wisdom that all cultures can agree on?
是否存在所有文化都能认同的智慧的某些内容哪？
A group of 34 researchers from all over the world and from fields like psychology, philosophy and anthropology got together to explore 'Dimensions of wisdom perception across twelve countries on five continents'.
来自心理学、哲学和人类学等领域的34名世界各地的研究人员聚集在一起，探索"五大洲十二个国家智慧感知的维度"。
The study found two characteristics that everyone – from urban university students in Peru to villagers in rural India – associated with wisdom.
该研究发现，每个人，从秘鲁的城市大学生到印度农村的村民，都认为智慧与两个特征有联系。
The first quality a wise person must have is 'socio-emotional awareness'.
智者必须具备的第一个品质是"社会情感意识"。
This is about the ability to understand others' point of view and really care about their thoughts and feelings.
这是指理解他人观点并真正关心他们想法和感受的能力。
However, this person must also have the second quality: 'reflective orientation', which is about using logic and past experience to make judgements.
然而，这个人还必须具备第二个品质："反思倾向"，即运用逻辑和过往经验做出判断。
If you are mindlessly driven by emotions and don't think before you act, then you are unlikely to be perceived as wise.
如果你被情绪盲目驱使，行动前不加思考，那么你不太可能被视为有智慧。
So, if you want to be wise, learn to both keep your cool and put yourself in others' shoes.
所以，如果你想变得智慧，既要学会保持冷静，也要学会换位思考。
But, while this study helps us build a more unified definition of wisdom, the world is vast and cultures vary hugely.
但是，虽然这项研究帮助我们树立了更统一的智慧定义，但世界广阔，文化差异巨大。
In 'The Cambridge Handbook of Wisdom', the authors make an apple pie analogy, comparing pie to wisdom.
在《剑桥智慧手册》中，作者做了一个苹果派的类比，将派比作智慧。
Imagine your grandmother makes your favourite apple pie – she represents the wisdom you think is best.
想象一下，你的祖母做了你最喜欢的苹果派——她呈现了你所认为最完美的智慧。
Now, imagine you take this apple pie to the Amazon rainforest, where apples don't grow.
现在，想象一下你把这个苹果派带到不长苹果的亚马逊雨林。
For the locals, the pie isn't as good as their own traditional desserts; they've grown up with different flavours and ingredients, just as different cultures have developed their own wisdom traditions.
对当地人来说，这个派不如他们自己的传统甜点；他们是在不同的风味和食材中长大的，就像不同的文化发展出了自己的智慧传统一样。
Ultimately, the way wisdom is experienced, shared, and valued depends on the cultural ingredients involved.
最终，智慧被体会、分享和重视的方式取决于其所涉及的文化因素。